<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ggplot2 on Paul Oldham&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>/tags/ggplot2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ggplot2 on Paul Oldham&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright @ Paul Oldham 2017-2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/ggplot2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Graphing Patent Data with ggplot2 part2</title>
      <link>/graphing-patent-data-with-ggplot2-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/graphing-patent-data-with-ggplot2-part2/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The Grammar of Graphics Getting Started Loading the Data Reviewing and Preparing the Dataset with dplyr Creating a Publication Country Table Creating a Publication Country by Year Table  Getting Going with ggplot in ggplot2 Establishing the Base Object Adding a geom Changing the Geom Adding a trend line Statistical Transformations Adding Labels Publication Country Charts A Bar chart Adding labels to columns A Ranked Bar Chart A Dot Plot A Balloon Plot A Stacked Bar Chart Faceting facet_wrap  Pie and Coxcomb Plots Creating a Pie Chart (aaaargh) The Coxcomb Plot  Round Up Useful Resources   Introduction This is Part 2 of an article introducing R for patent analytics that focuses on visualising patent data in R using the ggplot2 package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wrangling Pizza Patents in R</title>
      <link>/wrangling-pizza-patents-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/wrangling-pizza-patents-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Getting Started with R Getting Started About the pizza patent dataset Reading in the Data Creating a numeric field Renaming Columns Selecting Columns for plotting  Creating Counts Total by Year Round Up    This is the first part of a two part article on using R and the ggplot2 package to visualise patent data. In a previous article we looked at visualising pizza related patent activity in Tableau Public.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>