<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Open Source Patent Analytics</title>
    <link>/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Open Source Patent Analytics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright @ Paul Oldham 2017</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Importing Excel Data in R - A 2018 Update</title>
      <link>/2018/02/06/importing-excel-data-into-r-updated/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/06/importing-excel-data-into-r-updated/</guid>
      <description>Back in 2015 I wrote a long blog post on importing Excel tables into R. Happily for everyone this is now a lot easier than it was. This post provides an update on importing spreadsheets into R and exporting from R to Excel. I’ll also cover reading an excel file into R from a url as that seems to be an ongoing struggle.
Import Directly from the RStudio Menu The big change is that it is now very easy to import from Excel using the RStudio Menu: File &amp;gt; Import Dataset &amp;gt; From Excel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating an Infographic with infogram</title>
      <link>/2016/04/20/infographics-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/20/infographics-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>In this article we will use RStudio to prepare patent data for visualisation in an infographic using the online software tool infogram.
Infographics are a popular way of presenting data in a way that is easy for a reader to understand without reading a long report. Infographics are well suited to presenting summaries of data with simple messages about key findings. A good infographic can encourage the audience to read a detailed report and is a tool for engagement with audiences during presentations of the findings of patent research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Scientific Literature with rplos</title>
      <link>/2015/10/27/rplos-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/10/27/rplos-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this chapter we look at the use of the rplos package from rOpenSci to access the scientific literature from the Public Library of Science using the PLOS Search API.
The Public Library of Science (PLOS) is the main champion of open access peer reviewed scientific publications and has published somewhere in the region of 140,000 articles. These articles are a fantastic resource. PLOS includes the following titles.
 PLOS ONE PLOS Biology PLOS Medicine PLOS Computational Biology PLOS Genetics PLOS Pathogens PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases PLOS Clinical Trials () PLOS Collections (collections of articles)  PLOS is important because it provides open access to the full text of peer reviewed research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Patent Data with the Lens</title>
      <link>/2015/07/26/lens-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/26/lens-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this article we provide a brief introduction to The Lens patent database as a free source of data for patent analytics.
The Lens is a patent database based in Australia that describes itself as “an open global cyberinfrastructure to make the innovation system more efficient and fair, more transparent and inclusive.” The main way it seeks to do this is by providing access to patent information with a particular focus on sequence information as well as analysis of issues such as DNA related patent activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading and Writing an Excel File in R</title>
      <link>/2015/04/30/reading-and-writing-an-excel-file-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/04/30/reading-and-writing-an-excel-file-in-r/</guid>
      <description>This post was updated in 2018 and you can read it here
The CRAN Project has the following to say about importing Excel files into R.
“The first piece of advice is to avoid doing so if possible! If you have access to Excel, export the data you want from Excel in tab-delimited or comma-separated form, and use read.delim or read.csv to import it into R. (You may need to use read.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>