<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Patent Analytics on Open Source Patent Analytics</title>
    <link>/tags/patent-analytics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Patent Analytics on Open Source Patent Analytics</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright @ Paul Oldham 2017</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/patent-analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the earliest patent priority number</title>
      <link>/2018/02/09/identifying-the-earliest-patent-priority-number/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/02/09/identifying-the-earliest-patent-priority-number/</guid>
      <description>Introduction The international patent system as under the 1883 Paris Convention establishes a “priority” system it identify the earliest filing of an invention. In cases where an invention is filed by different applicants the priority number and date allows for the identification of the priority applicant. That is, the person or organisation that was the first to file for the claimed invention.
The priority system is also important in patents stastics and economic analysis for two main reasons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating an Infographic with infogram</title>
      <link>/2016/04/20/infographics-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/04/20/infographics-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>In this article we will use RStudio to prepare patent data for visualisation in an infographic using the online software tool infogram.
Infographics are a popular way of presenting data in a way that is easy for a reader to understand without reading a long report. Infographics are well suited to presenting summaries of data with simple messages about key findings. A good infographic can encourage the audience to read a detailed report and is a tool for engagement with audiences during presentations of the findings of patent research.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessing Patent Data with the Lens</title>
      <link>/2015/07/26/lens-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/26/lens-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this article we provide a brief introduction to The Lens patent database as a free source of data for patent analytics.
The Lens is a patent database based in Australia that describes itself as “an open global cyberinfrastructure to make the innovation system more efficient and fair, more transparent and inclusive.” The main way it seeks to do this is by providing access to patent information with a particular focus on sequence information as well as analysis of issues such as DNA related patent activity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of Patent Analytics Tools</title>
      <link>/2015/07/26/overview-patent-analytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/07/26/overview-patent-analytics/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This article provides an overview of the open source and free software tools that are available for patent analytics. The aim of the chapter is to serve as a quick reference guide for some of the main tools in the tool kit.
This article is now a chapter in the WIPO Manual on Open Source Patent Analytics. You can read the chapter in electronic book format here and find all the materials including presentations at the WIPO Analytics Github homepage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Network Visualisation with Gephi</title>
      <link>/2015/05/17/gephi-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/17/gephi-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Introduction This article focuses on visualising patent data in networks using the open source software Gephi.
Gephi is one of a growing number of free network analysis and visualisation tools with others including Cytoscape, Tulip, GraphViz, Pajek for Windows, and VOSviewer to name but a few. In addition, network visualisation packages are available for R and Python. We have chosen to focus on Gephi because it is a good all round network visualisation tool that is quite easy to use and to learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualising Data with Tableau Public</title>
      <link>/2015/05/17/tableau-tutorial/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/05/17/tableau-tutorial/</guid>
      <description>Introduction In this article we will be analysing and visualising patent data using Tableau Public.
Tableau Public is a free version of Tableau Desktop and provides a very good practical introduction to the use of patent data for analysis and visualisation. In many cases Tableau Public will represent the standard that other open source and free tools will need to meet.
This is a practical demonstration of the use of Tableau in patent analytics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>